at the simile of the six
animals suppose monks a man catches six animals
suppose monks a man catches six animals
of different domains
and different resorts a snake a
crocodile bird dog a jackal and a monkey
bird dog a jackal and a monkey
tethering each with a strong rope
having tethered them with a strong rope
he fastens the rope together in the
middle let's go over them now amongst these six
let's go over them now amongst these six
animals of different domains and feeding
habits would swing around and struggle
each trying to get to the to his natural
domain the snake would struggle the crocodile
the snake would struggle the crocodile
and so on
now amongst when those six hungry
animals grow
weary they would yield to the one that
was the strongest
go his way and be under his power
in the same way monks whenever a monk
fails to practice
and develop mindfulness as to the body
the eye struggles to draw him towards
attractive objects
while unattractive objects are repellent
to him
and so on this monk is
his lack of restraint and what monks is
restraint so instead of he ties all those animals
so instead of he ties all those animals
to a strong post
and then they all pull in their
different directions
grow tired and stay right there and that
post is mindfulness of the body
so the would you can you have
a restrain of the six senses so
including your mind
without the without the right context
without like if you don't have
perspective in regard to the all of the six senses
in regard to the all of the six senses
so without a perspective can you
restrain them
no no because you're already pulled
that's what non-perspective
lack of perspective means you're down
the the pull of
a sense or all the senses that's why
people don't have
like people who engage with sensuality
that would have called centrality
weakness of wisdom
weakness of perspective weakness of
things that you know
because you get pulled down the down the
the pathway
of a sense of that wild animal so you
cannot sustain perspective and at the
same time go down the rabbit hole
impossible you either allow and go down the rabbit
you either allow and go down the rabbit
hole or you sustain the perspective
the reason why i'm bringing perspective
the perspective up is because people
would often think that
mindfulness of the body means like
feeling the body here
like feeling the sensations or it means
i'm mindful of this body
the mindfulness of the body is the
fundamental perspective in regard to
your own world as in the presence of the
body there
as sadi patana sutra says so the body
there is the basis for these six animals to
is the basis for these six animals to
which they are tied to
whether they want or not you can't have
centos without the body
without a unit of the body that's a
mindfulness of the body would mean
mindfulness of the perspective in regard
to all the six
senses that you have
so it's not a physical way of like
method practice of staying in the body
it's on the level of knowledge of the
body there it's nature
it's post from which these senses want
to pull left and right
but yes if you contemplate the nature of
that body as the buddha would say
as as something that is unownable
subject to illness death and so on
no pleasure of the senses within the
container of the body would be able to
overwhelm that perspective
if it's totally developed
but if you see your body as not mine
that's the right perspective well yeah
if you see the body on the right level
as not mine not just oh yes this body is
not mine
and if you think you're seeing the body
on the right level
as not mine you see while i'm seeing the
body on the right level as not mine is there
on the right level as not mine is there
passion and liability to passion in this
mind is the aversion and liability to
is the aversion and liability to
aversion in this mind is the distraction
ability of distraction in this mind
if the answer to any of those is yes
that's not the right level
because seeing the body on the right
level it is impenetrable
to passion aversion delusion so if you
with the mind
not above passion aversion delusion and
liability to passion aversion delusion
thinks this is the right level of the
mindfulness of the body well
you're confusing yourself that is a
serious misconception
because of which you will then not make
the effort to find what the right level
is the level but it's not
that is not liable to greed aversion and
delusion
so what way how do we be mindful of the
body well to understanding it's um well one
well to understanding it's um well one
way would be to understanding its nature
not just to like because i said be
mindful of the body and you have some
idea about it
and now you're doing it but instead of
focusing on doing the mindfulness of the
body focus on understanding the idea of
what you think mindfulness of the body
is
because people just take that idea of
granted so i hear mindfulness of the
body as an instruction and whatever comes to
as an instruction and whatever comes to
my mind that i do
is mindfulness of the body well isn't
that fortunate
if it was if it was so but then you know
it's the
it's the idea that's for the context the
right context the wrong context
basically right idea wrong idea or right
ideas wrong ideas
so yeah you're going to have some notion
of the mindfulness of the body and some
notion of the sense restraint
and you have to do it in the sense of
you have to be sense restrained
but instead of taking the notion for
granted through which you just keep
doing this
technique of mindfulness of the body or
whatever it is for you you actually keep
dwelling on the notion
and clarify it further does it
correspond to what the suit is described
does it make you dispassionate
completely even when you're not
momentarily focused on the body
is it an anchor that allows you to then
move around
dispassionate not liable to anger not
liable to delusion
or is it something that you're
dispassionate and not angry and so on
only when you're focusing on the body in
which case that's not mindfulness for
the body that's just you replacing one
object with the other object
so you've got to have some idea you will
have some idea
and then but you can't forget about that
idea you have to practice it exactly
so you want to be upgrading the idea
behind in other words you want to be developing
in other words you want to be developing
understanding not just
whatever you assumed mindfulness or body
is is what it is
and now you're just doing it
because if that mindfulness of the body
were the correct mindfulness of the body
you would be at least undergone you
would have no more
central pull
because when the mindfulness of the body
is understood to the extent necessary
you're enlightened
so people conflate um understanding
like um fulfilling the understanding
of mindfulness of the body in this case
with doing enough of mindfulness of the body
doing enough of mindfulness of the body
that i just assumed
mindfulness to be
but it's like okay maybe you were lucky
maybe your assumption of the mindfulness
was really correct right from the start
but what's the chance of that
today and also how many years have you
been doing it
and are there the results to show for
even when you're not mindful of the body
with your effort
because that's that's why people would
also like fall into the view that
oh yeah this is the dispassion it's
because yeah there is no passion
and and and ill will and current
delusion when you're actively making
this effort to be focused on body or
something because that object in itself of your
because that object in itself of your
focusing
yeah it's not arising in passion and so
on but are you liable
when you stop the focusing will the
passion come back means there is no
understanding that has taken root
which would have stayed regardless of
whether you're focusing on the body or
not so it's same with the sense restraint so
so it's same with the sense restraint so
the five animals
it's not just well the problem it's not
that the final
five animals want to go and feed in
these different domains
uh the problem is that you don't know
how to not identify with them
in other words you don't know how to not
take them as mine
when i wants to see something ears want
to hear something
your first starting point is i want to
see something i want to hear something
and then you hammer down the restraint
on yourself
and that's very strange is unpleasant
because there is an inherent discrepancy
there
that's why i say you cut you you
shouldn't be trying to get rid of these
things you should restrain yourself but you can
you should restrain yourself but you can
only do that correctly on the basis of
allowing these things to
endure so your eyes want to see
something you restrain eyes from seeing but you
you restrain eyes from seeing but you
don't ignore the fact that eyes want to
see something that's unpleasant that's how
something that's unpleasant that's how
you get to
basically outline the domain of the eye
that you realize okay
i this is what an eye does
you don't want to strangle the eye well
exactly yeah because you
and you will be strangling the eye so to
speak because you are identified with it
so it's self-destruct that's the only
way out that you can see
but even the simile it says it's these
six animals
that they are tied to and they will pull
everybody else so you are the one
that should be in charge of the tie of
the six animals now people buy them
but the reason you pull by them is
because you you don't
you cannot um cease to identify with it
when the pull is there first you feel
like you're being pulled in that
direction and that's how you have to start so you
and that's how you have to start so you
start with being pulled
you start by not giving in to the pool
but if all you do is just try to get
rid of the pool you're basically trying
to remove the senses
trying to kill the animals that still
doesn't make you in charge
that just kills the animals that so if
someone said yeah i would
i would not see sights with my eyes
that's how i'm free
i will not hear sounds with my ears and
they will say well you're no different
in a blind and a deaf man
so you're not free at all you just have
one animal left pulling you around but
you don't need six it's enough for one
of them to pull it around and for as
long as you're alive you will at least
have one at least your mind even if all
your senses fail
you're kind of locked inside syndrome or
something you have your mind and that
mind will be pulling you now
in the place of all other five so the
point is to you
not be pulled through identification
with that sense
not to not have the sense pulling
through non-identification yeah no and
when i say no identification
again it should not be understood like
as a matter of choice i choose to
identify no by not being able to resist the pull
no by not being able to resist the pull
by not having the clear context and
perspective in regard to the senses
you are automatically identified so you
can't just choose to say this is not
mine but you can set yourself up so that
but you can set yourself up so that
you're unable to take it as mine
and you set yourself up but actually
sustaining the perspective
in regard to the various pulling sensors
like you're contrasting now these senses
against a better
more wholesome broader perspective
that corresponds closer to the actual
universal truth
the real characteristics of the senses
and then you get to see oh yeah truly
these are the five
six wild animals i have a choice
i can allow them to run wild and then
pay the price as a result of it
like uh i don't know if it's the same
suit or the other way it says
like if i if i let this car go and eat
whatever he wants
my ox if i let it then you know the
owner will complain to the police they
come and they beat me up they flogged me
they find me
because it was my book i'm responsible
for it
so i don't i don't let it go and eat
anywhere wherever he wants
so i don't incur suffering on account of
it
i don't get out of control or same like
like as i said imagine like
you know you're tied to five dogs six
dogs and if you allow them one of them to
and if you allow them one of them to
pull they will gain the momentum and
then they'll be dragging you around
you won't be able to stand you and then
if they choose to go
through the rocky terrain and thrown it
around you will you won't you can't oh
now i want to stop now it's too late
it will stop when it's running when it
runs when it runs its cause
and by that time you might be like
beaten to death
as a result of of those desires and wild
animals so in that sense you're not trying to
so in that sense you're not trying to
strangle the senses you're trying to
maintain a better perspective in the
sense of indirectly know
that oh if i were to let this sense go
out there now
is a good likelihood it will see
something hear something taste something
they will then result in its increased
excitement that then i will have to deal
with
so it's better for me to not allow it
then i don't have to deal with it so i
abide in peace here and now
as opposed to having to then spend all
this effort to calm the sense down
calm the animal down no just prevent it
from being excited in the first place
and the more you do that the more you
maintain that perspective regardless of
what what sense is pulling you
the clearer than the nature of that
relationship with the senses becomes in
other words
less and less identified with them you
are that's why anagam is in arahants in
the suttas when the mara would try to
tempt him through the senses they would
refer to the
the the center six senses the body the
person they would say
who are you talking about none of this
is mine this is just a creature there
it's still the five six functioning
senses but in the same sense you from your
but in the same sense you from your
point of view would see a dog
a bird a monkey another person and now
there is this creature as well so
there's a creature there
creature creature oh and there's this
creature that's always paired with me
because of which i used to assume it's
mine because there was no other creature
as close as this creature
to my point of view but now i understand
that's not mine either
that's how it's regarded we we usually
regard our own creature our own selves
as
our own as the closest friend so to
speak the most intimate thing that it's
your own thoughts with yourself
but actually you should regard that also
as not yours as a stranger
that doesn't mean you well necessarily
so the creature is there you're paired
with it the six senses
you have no choice to be apart from the
six senses but you have a choice whether
they get excited or not
and whether you're gonna have to be
dealing with it or not
so that's why he guards the sense doors
you don't chase the sense object to try
to get rid of the sense objects
you don't try to shut the eyes down or
pull the eyes out or cut the ears off
you got the sense doors in other words
you know
before the eye sees ears here and so on
is this leading towards lust or towards
this passion towards anger or
lack of anger and so on and if there was
last you guard the door you don't let
the animal
same like imagine you're holding dog dog
is calm and you see there is a deer
coming the dog still hasn't spotted it
what would you do kill the dog quickly
before it sees the deer so you don't
have to deal with it well
you kill the dog you kill yourself
because you are the creature shoot the
deer before it comes
yeah good luck so what would you do in
that instance
here you are five dogs both hands
leashes they're calm and there is a big smelly
they're calm and there is a big smelly
deer coming the way just behind the bend
and you see the dogs don't see it
well you turn around turn around
yeah i mean if you can't turn around
well you just get their attention to
make them sit down
set them up so they're not basically
directly exposed
if you can't do that either would you do
then tie them no you hold them on the leashes
tie them no you hold them on the leashes
yeah yeah you hold them down
you dig your heels in yeah twist the
leashes twice around your hands
and pull down and hold either way
any of those things the result is the
same they
must not chase the deer so in other
words uh
for this until you're like beyond
sensuality and so on
the animals will get excited but you
don't want to be contributing towards
that and that's that whole like
um i can't remember the exact suture but
when the buddha says you know or you
think the opposite
or you think something else but if you
can't do any of that you crush your mind
with the mind
like longer man would pin down the weak
man until he comes down
so even if the dogs are now you couldn't
prevent the excitement as it will
inevitably happen at some point
because you didn't foresee the deer soon
enough you were careless
or whatever now they're excited still
it's better to endure and not give in to
the pool than to let it and then become
the dogs and get him that identify with
a creature
and and the more you practice that then
the clearer also the danger of allowing
it becomes
because when all you're used to is being
dragged around and surfing on the
leashes of various wild animals
you don't see the danger because you're
just used to the constant movement and
also that's what
that's what you're training them to
become for sure you're training them to
be one yeah
that's exactly how the passion works
that's what the buddha means by the
diversification prolific proliferation
or or multiplying
so you choose the singleness of no as
opposed to diversity
of spread in every direction and then
one there two there's six days fox
rabbit uh squirrel
so that's what people think singleness
of mind
is with where you kind of at the end of
this proliferation you find
a point that all proliferation sees no
singleness is actually when you undo all
the proliferation and find a point
before things proliferate and then you choose
things proliferate and then you choose
to stay on that level and protect it
guarding the door one entrance one
pointedness you know one pointed because you stared
you know one pointed because you stared
at the deer you don't see anything else
you're one pointed
because your point is none of this
situation will change
doesn't matter whether deer or squirrel
or whatever comes in here
dogs will not run and if they're used to
running all the time
they're going to be pulling a lot in the
beginning untrained
animal so same with you if you
haven't been really developing and
clarifying perspective
in regard to the sense restraint if you
just been doing it blindly
it's still going to hurt but once the
perspective is there the singleness of
mind that unity so to speak of
that unity so to speak of
non-diversified in different direction
and so on
remains even while the sense is excited
and there is no identification with it
because there is no perspective loss
so you in the creature your your point
of view in regard to the creature and
the thoughts of the creature and the
plans of the creature and the sight
sounds melting touches of the creature
none of the viewers in that sense but
not no no not mine not mine to dismiss
it but
not mine because it's there and i have
perspective in regard to it not my dogs
exactly not my dogs yeah that's often
the response
or denial or acceptance oh well that's
what the dogs do
well yes but you don't have to suffer
and counter it because
the trained dog wouldn't do that so you
can't say that's what all the dogs do
you need to qualify that statement and
say that's what the untrained dogs do
which now highlights you have a choice
to train or to untrain
and that's what we'll say untrained eye
untrained ear untrained senses untrained mind in
ear untrained senses untrained mind in
regard to the senses that's what it
would do
so you train it take responsibility for
the lyco training and train it
and the clearer your perspective is the
more it becomes obvious it's an indirect
training so it's kind of sensitive
strain is actually effortlessly done
rightly as well
because it's on the basis of mindfulness
which you can't have too much of and it
is effortless if done rightly
all you need to do and even if the
excitement happens it's not your
excitement and you know doesn't matter how much
and you know doesn't matter how much
this dog is excited he's not going
anywhere
so then he comes down you might have to
hear it listen to the yapping but that's
the disturbance
that you have to accept on the level
that arihant accepts the disturbance
left on account of this body until the
aggregates break apart
but for sure his animals will not be
able to pull him anymore
ever again at all done so he senses that
in his control
their spirit has been broken in a way
some people they've maintained
they've been well tamed and trained and
obedient so now both are dwelling at ease because
so now both are dwelling at ease because
senses are happier as well
that's then the pleasure of jhana and
you know touching the pleasure with the
body in the
meditation is done correctly and so on
it's more pleasant
to be peaceful even for the wild animals
but they can't help themselves but you
can and by doing so you're helping yourself
and by doing so you're helping yourself
as well training the creature
that is you
that's exactly like training dogs it's
often the simulator taming an elephant
taming an ox um little buddha using the
elephant
but you as i said the difference is
whether you you're kind of projecting it
externally or no you still have to
seeing yourself your five
six senses has five six dogs
and they'll have their different little
traits and little characteristics and
little kind of preferences
but you are the one and again you don't
trade them by constantly choking them
and holding on to them
you train them by seeing more than what
they see
by maintaining the background to their
own actions that they are not aware of
look he's running like a maniac now and
there are balls there
he doesn't see it and when he does it
will be too late
now imagine you're tied to that dog it's
dragging you well the wild boys are
angry with little babies
so now my life is at stake so i better
do something about it
you can't just oh it's not my problem
so in order to stop identifying with the
six animals that your creature is
you have to take it um you have to take
them up personally first
you have to actually see that you are at
stake here
if you let your mind run eyes ears nose
and so on
you will pay the price not them
so i better take it this personally
and taking it personally you tame them
eventually and then you cannot
then identify with them because you
can't lose perspective now
and patience you know that's the what's
any even the basic dog training first thing
even the basic dog training first thing
they say you must be patient
and imagine how much more when it comes
to training yourself
as a creature of the sex
the wild man you know the wild man yeah
everybody's a wild creature